<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[A briefe collection or epitomie of all the notable and material things contained in the hystorie of Guicchiardine being verie necessarie for Parliament, councell, treatises, and negotiations.]</title>
            <author>Guicciardini, Francesco, 1483-1540.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 54 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02333</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118301</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853508</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853508</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18892</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02333)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18892)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 888:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[A briefe collection or epitomie of all the notable and material things contained in the hystorie of Guicchiardine being verie necessarie for Parliament, councell, treatises, and negotiations.]</title>
                  <author>Guicciardini, Francesco, 1483-1540.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 51 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T. Purfoote,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title taken from caption on B1r; imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaf A1 blank, except for signature mark on recto.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks title page, A2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Italy --  History --  1492-1559.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Brian Matzke</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18892:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18892:1"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull Sir Henrie Brooke Cobham Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the hiſtorie of Guicchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardine hath wonne ſufficient credite in mens opinions to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance it ſelfe againſt the enuious: I hope my boldnes may much the better bee excuſed, preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to publiſh in print this treatiſe containing all the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and materiall things in that Hyſtorie: whoſoeuer hee
<pb facs="tcp:18892:2"/> was that hath beſtowed his trauaile to reduce ſo great a volume into ſo ſmall and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie a Booke (though his name be ſuppreſſed) hee may merit, no doubt, his due com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation: I thought it a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie office for me to make ſhew of my good diſpoſition, in due conſideration towards you whom I haue knowne of along time to be exerciſed in forraine affaires, and imploied in matters of ſome weight for her Maieſties ſeruice and the eſtate: Hauing thereon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted my ſelfe to thinke you meete to receyue this little
<pb facs="tcp:18892:2"/> Booke into your protection, which moſt affectionatly I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend vnto you, with my prayers vnto the eternall God for your worſhips health and long life.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my houſe in the new rents in Saint Nicho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las ſhambles, <date>this ſeuenth of December. 1591.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt humbly at commaund, T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18892:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18892:3"/>
            <head>A briefe collection or Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of all the notable and material things contained in the hyſtorie of Guicchiardine: being verie neceſſarie for Parliament, councell, treatiſes, and nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations.</head>
            <div type="book">
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Odouike Sforce,</hi> tutor and vncle to <hi>Iohn Galeas,</hi> duke of Millaine, fearing leaſt <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of Naples ſhould make war vpon him, departed from the league lately made betweene him, the king, &amp; the Florentines againſt the Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans: and cloſely procureth <hi>Charles</hi> the viii. king of France to come to Italie to conquer the kingdome of Naples, as due to the houſe of Aniow: for that Pope <hi>Vrbin</hi> the fourth, gaue Naples and Cicill, being the olde fee of the Church, vnto <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince, and Aniow, brother vnto Saint <hi>Lewis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> was verie ſecure, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb facs="tcp:18892:4"/> men are in their woorſt deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, knowing his ſtrength both by ſea and land, and knowing withall that there was no great matter in his enemie: but he remembred not the weakeneſſe and parcialities in Italie, and that France was not ſince <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> time ſo great in circuite, nor flouriſhing in ſouldiers. Howbeit he treated with <hi>Lodouike</hi> for amitie (who ſecretly promiſed him) meaning no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, and with <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt (lately choſen Pope by open ſymonie, and by the meanes of Cardinall <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canio Sforce,</hi> in deſpite of the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Saint <hi>Peters ad Vincula</hi>) who before was ſecretly confederated with <hi>Lodouike,</hi> and yet promiſed <hi>Ferdinand</hi> that he would defend Naples, and <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> ſhould defend the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> further made peace with <hi>Maximilian</hi> king of Romans, lately choſen Emperour: <hi>Lodouike</hi> on the other ſide, to winne the Emperour from him, gaue in mariage to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Marie Blanche</hi> ſiſter of <hi>Iohn
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18892:4"/> Galeas,</hi> with promiſe of foure hundred thouſand ducats, whereupon the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour more eſteeming the mony, then his new brother in law, gaue the inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duchie of Millain vnto <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douike:</hi> pretending that ſince the death of <hi>Philip Viſcont Mary</hi> there had bene no lawfull duke thereof.</p>
               <p>The French king hereupon ſent <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron de la Baſcha,</hi> embaſſadour to the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Florentines,</hi> and the <hi>Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans:</hi> where albeit he receiued onely comforts in generalitie, (for that the warres were put off till the next yeare) yet <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſeeing all things now like to come to naught, fel into penſiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſo into an Apoplexie, &amp; died, whoſe ſonne <hi>Alfonſo</hi> ſucceeded, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred league with Pope <hi>Alexander,</hi> as his father did. But diſcouering the trecheries of <hi>Lodouike,</hi> he ſent away his ambaſſadour, he ſequeſtred the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues of the duchie of <hi>Barrie,</hi> and by all meanes endeuoured alſo to alienate from him the citie of <hi>Geane:</hi> yea (that which the deuil himſelf would ſcarcely
<pb facs="tcp:18892:5"/> haue done) he ſent to the Turke <hi>Baiazet Ottoman,</hi> aſſuring him that <hi>Charles</hi> the French king after the conqueſt of Italie, had a meaning to ſet vppon Greece, and therefore he ſhould helpe in this common caſe. He ſent his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew forthwith to ſurpriſe <hi>Geane:</hi> but <hi>Lois</hi> duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> preuented him.</p>
               <p>Now began Italie to thinke of her weakenes, &amp; the Pope commanded the king not to enter: <hi>Peter de Medices</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Florentines (who were euer French heretofore) declared them ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the king: the Venecians were content to ſtande neuter. <hi>Lodouike</hi> vpon better aduice, began to feare that the conquering Naples, would alſo ſwallow vp Millaine, and therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan now to caſt how to make an accord as ſoone as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king were paſt the Alpes: hoping to make <hi>Alphonſo</hi> tributarie to France, and thereby to aſſure his owne eſtate. Now began prodigious ſights to be ſeene: as in <hi>Puglia,</hi> three Sunnes enuironed with cloudes, and horrible thundering. In <hi>Arezzo</hi> armies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18892:5"/> of men and horſes, in the aire, with drummes and trumpets, and diuerſe Images ſweating.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Colonoys</hi> ioine with the French, <hi>Lodouike</hi> accompanieth them, <hi>Peter de Medices</hi> becommeth his friend, and the Piſans, the Pope, the Venecians, and <hi>Lodouike</hi> in greater feare then euer tofore: for that <hi>Charles</hi> paſſed like a thunder through Italie, with great ſucceſſe. <hi>Charles</hi> entereth Rome, kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Popes feete, and ioyneth with him in league defenſiue: the Cardinall of <hi>Valence,</hi> ſonne to the Pope, is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed three monethes to followe the king toward Naples.</p>
               <p>The Neapolitans ſhew that they neither loued <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the father, nor <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the ſonne, which brought him in great perplexitie, and ſo much the more, for that the ſpirite of <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> (as it was thought) appeared to his chiefe ſurgeon, willing him to tell <hi>Alfonſo,</hi> that it was in vain for him to reſiſt the French king, it was determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their race ſhould faile in reſpect of
<pb facs="tcp:18892:6"/> diuerſe their great ſinnes, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the thing that they reſolued in Saint <hi>Leonards</hi> Church in <hi>Chiaie,</hi> which was to put a number of the novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to death. Hereupon <hi>Alfonſo</hi> tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented in conſcience, priuily ſtole a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way into <hi>Sicilia,</hi> with foure gallies, whereby the French king with great eaſe got this noble kingdome: as the <hi>Romane</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Veni, vidi, vici.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beit, <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſonne of <hi>Alfonſo</hi> tooke on him the title of the king, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the kingdome. But within ſhort ſpace hee was driuen to flie into <hi>Iskia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this time the noble captaine <hi>Iean Iaques de Trinulce</hi> of <hi>Capua.</hi> gaue himſelfe to the king, and offered to bring <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to ſome good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: whereof the king willingly accepted: ſo that hee woulde forgo Naples, in reſpect whereof, he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to giue him other eſtates in Fraunce. This was the fruite of diſcorde and ambition in the manie little eſtates of Italie, whereof none
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18892:6"/> was able to defende it ſelfe ſeueral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ioyntly might haue done grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="book">
               <head>The ſecond Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>Piſans</hi> deſire to caſt off the yoke of the <hi>Florentines,</hi> and ſubmit themſelues to the French: the <hi>Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> prepare to warre vpon them, and in the meane time fall at diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence among them ſelues for the forme of their owne gouernement: touching the which <hi>Soderin</hi> and <hi>Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucci</hi> made two excellent Orations, one for <hi>Democratie,</hi> the other for <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocratie,</hi> the which had preuailed, had not the authoritie of Frier <hi>Sauinorola</hi> carried it away, who like a Prophet in the middeſt of their quietneſſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolde them all the miſeries of Italie by ſtrangers to come.</p>
               <p>The Pope is ſuſpected to haue poiſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Gemin Ottoman,</hi> being corrupted
<pb facs="tcp:18892:7"/> thereunto by the Turke, for feare hee ſhoulde aide the French king againſt him, after his conqueſt of Italie, <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uike Sforce</hi> and the Venetians, ſeeing the incredible ſucceſſe of king <hi>Charles,</hi> feared now bondage to themſelues, and began to league together, bringing thereunto the Pope, the king of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes, and the king of Spaine. The Florentines were alſo dealt withall, but what for feare, and what for loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to leeſe the traffike of Fraunce they helde backe.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the king heard of this league, yet he cauſed himſelfe to be crowned before hee woulde depart from Naples, and treated verie earneſt amitie with the Pope, who made to him faire ſemblant and promiſe, and yet he ſo little truſted the king, that at his returne from Naples by Rome, the Pope forſooke Rome, and went ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to <hi>Orbieta,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rugia,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Ancona,</hi> to haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie of the ſea, if neede ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. The king in the mean time paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18892:7"/> by <hi>Siena,</hi> and <hi>Piſa,</hi> and the confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates had a meaning to ſtop his paſſage into France: but their hearts fayled them at the firſt. After aſſembling an armie neere the riuer <hi>Taro,</hi> vnder the conduct of the marques of <hi>Mantua,</hi> they fought a long battell, where the baſtard of <hi>Burbon</hi> was ſlaine, and the king almoſt taken priſoner, had he not bene well horſed: and yet in the ende the Frenchmen had the honour of the field, at which time it was noted that the ſouldiers of <hi>Lodouike</hi> would not fight, as though he had bene in as much danger of the Venetians, as of the Frenchmens victorie.</p>
               <p>The inſolent gouernement of the Frenchmen (who can better win then keepe) became odious, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ferdinand</hi> in hope to recouer Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. But at the firſt incounter, his horſe was ſlaine vnder him, and himſelf had beene vndoubtedly ſlaine, had not an olde page of his, brother to the duke of <hi>Termini,</hi> horſed him vpon his owne horſe, and ſuffred himſelfe to be ſlaine
<pb facs="tcp:18892:8"/> for him, a rare example in our time. Within a while after the <hi>Nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politans</hi> of themſelues receyued <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand,</hi> and the Frenchmen retyre to the Caſtell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nouaria</hi> and other places are beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the king, and the Bailie of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uion,</hi> who being willed by the king to ſend for ten thouſand <hi>Switchers,</hi> there came twentie thouſand at the compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Nouaria:</hi> and a peace begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to be treated betweene the king and <hi>Lodouike:</hi> touching the which, <hi>Monſieur de la Tremouille,</hi> and the prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> made two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie Orations, and the duke of <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance</hi> gaineſayd the peace ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he gaue the prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> the lie. Howbeit the king and the greater part being inclined to peace, and deſirous to returne into France, the king departed ſuddenly to <hi>Thurin,</hi> for that the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured, threatning to take him pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner for lacke of pay: for that <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleuenth, was woont euer
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18892:8"/> to pay them for three moneths: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the king was faine to yeelde, though he were eſcaped himſelfe out of their daungers, for that they had taken priſoners the Bailie of <hi>Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and other Captaines. At the time that the Frenchmen helde Naples, the horrible diſeaſe of the pockes, a thing then vncurable, began in moſt pitifull vlcers and cankers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="book">
               <head>The third Booke.</head>
               <p>THis vnwiſe and ſudden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of king <hi>Charles,</hi> put all Italie in hope to be at reſt from any more ſuch plagues, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt <hi>Lodouike</hi> thinking that he had ſo farre offended the king, as it was but follie to keepe that peace, which he neuer meant further then for the holding of <hi>Nouaria,</hi> and for his own ſafetie, ſearched forthwith ſome honeſt colour to ſlippe from the king, and
<pb facs="tcp:18892:9"/> to ſet ſome other ſtates at oddes with him, which hee did with ſuch ſucceſſe, that he termed himſelfe, <hi>The ſonne of Fortune.</hi> And yet within a while after, hearing of the kings full reſolution to returne againe into Italie, he was marueilouſly perplexed, inſomuch that once againe he practiſed capitulations with the king: wherein he would haue accorded euery article, ſauing that they could neuer truſt one another by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great iniuries ſecretly paſſed and yet certainly knowne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> in the meane time with all diligence beſtirreth himſelfe, taketh <hi>Nuceria,</hi> treateth with the Venetians, who accept of his friendſhip (and take <hi>Piſa</hi> into protection) ioyneth with the Marques of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and fought with <hi>Mont Penſier,</hi> and his Switchers at <hi>Nuceria,</hi> and by reaſon of the ſlacknes of king <hi>Charles,</hi> who neither kept ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment in comming himſelfe, nor ſending ſuccours, preuayled greatly in the kingdome of Naples. But alas ſo deſtinie would, he died in the middeſt of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18892:9"/> his hope and glorie without children (according to the viſion) being the firſt king of that Realme, within three yeeres: whom his vncle <hi>Don Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> ſucceeded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lodouike</hi> ſeeing the French kings returne into Italy begin to wax cold, he became verie iollie, and thinking to ſerue his turne with the king of Romanes, as he had done by the king of France, that is to ſay, to terrifie the great eſtates, and in the meane time to gaine the ſmaller, he perſwaded with ſixe hundred thouſand ducats <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> to come into Italie. <hi>Maximilian</hi> on the other ſide meant as ſubtilly, as he ſecretly, purpoſing to win the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Naples for <hi>Iohn</hi> heire to the king of Spaine, his ſonne in law: which <hi>Lodouike</hi> perceyuing, was ſore aſtoniſhed, and yet in the end wan him to <hi>Fredericke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Venetians became now iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of <hi>Maximilian,</hi> and <hi>Lodouike,</hi> and therefore ſent <hi>Hannibal Bentiuole</hi> to Piſa, and ſo much the rather, for that
<pb facs="tcp:18892:10"/> they being troubled by <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and otherwiſe, and forſaken in their need by the Frenchmen, were dealt withall by <hi>Lodouike,</hi> to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to <hi>Maximilian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope thinking himſelfe now to haue opportunitie to occupie the eſtates of the <hi>Vrſins,</hi> the chiefe of them being detained at <hi>Naples,</hi> declared <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginio,</hi> and the reſt rebels, for taking ſolde of the French, and ſo ioyning with the <hi>Colonoys,</hi> aſſayled them on all ſides, to the diſpleaſure of the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians,</hi> who meant to gaine that fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: but that in theſe daungerous times, opportunitie ſerued not to fall out with the Pope. <hi>Lodouike</hi> albeit that he profeſſed himſelfe altogether to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> extolling <hi>Iohn Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leas,</hi> the firſt duke of <hi>Millaine,</hi> who made them executors of his teſtament, and acknowledging that to their great charge thei had defended his eſtate: yet his teeth ſo watred at <hi>Piſa,</hi> which they had gotten, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cauſed the Pope &amp; the Emperor to perſwade, that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18892:10"/> to reſtore <hi>Piſa,</hi> to <hi>Florence,</hi> for feare of giuing cauſe of the French kings returne: thinking vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution to get it himſelfe: but the <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> ambaſſador impugned it with greater reaſons.</p>
               <p>At this time <hi>Aluiano</hi> aſſiſted by the <hi>Guelphes,</hi> ſacked the houſes of the <hi>Gibellins,</hi> and ſlue Liii. of the chiefe in the Popes territorie, who nothing hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the matter: but ſee the plague of God, his yonger ſonne the Cardinal of <hi>Valence</hi> ſlue his elder brother duke of <hi>Candie,</hi> as he rode alone one night in the citie of Rome, for that he thought him to haue greater fauour of their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Lucrece</hi> than himſelfe: in whom as it is thought, the father had as good part as either of them both.</p>
               <p>The French king made peace with Spain &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Switchers,</hi> &amp; ment to return into Italy: but pleaſures, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of S. <hi>Malo</hi> detained him. In the meane time he dieth, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the xii. duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> ſucceedeth. At the ſame time <hi>Sauinorola</hi> was by the Pope put to death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:18892:11"/>
               <head>The fourth Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ewes</hi> the twelfth entitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe king of Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Naples, and Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill, and duke of Millaine, entending to conquer the dukedome. <hi>Lodouike Sforce</hi> being yet more iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Venetians, then of him, ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Florentines to recouer Piſa: the Pope on the other ſide ſecretly bent to fauour the French king, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereby vnawares of the reſt to gaine many things, and in the end the kingdome of Naples, practiſing in the meane time with <hi>Fredericke,</hi> to marry his daughter to his ſonne the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Valence, wherein <hi>Lodouike</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo played a part, ſhewing him what a ſtrengthening it ſhould be to him, and what a weakning to the French king: but <hi>Fredericke</hi> truſting neither of both, vtterly refuſed, which bredde much trouble and practiſe.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18892:11"/>
               <p>The Florentines offer accord to the Venetians, but it will not be receyued: For ſtill they defend <hi>Piſa.</hi> The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of Valence before the Pope and his Cardinals, renounceth his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals hat: and prepareth to go into France, where he was from Cardinal of <hi>Valence</hi> made duke of <hi>Valence,</hi> a citie in <hi>Daulphinoys</hi> by the French king, for that the Pope had promiſed him to diuorce the French Queene for ſterilitie, which he performed. Hauing this new ſouldier, the king made peace with all his neighbours, and bendeth towards Italie, and requireth <hi>Piſa</hi> to be left in his hands. The Venetians are in great doubt, whether they may ioyne with the king, or no. <hi>Grimanni</hi> and <hi>Treuiſan</hi> make excellent orations to that purpoſe: in the ende they ioyne, and that in ſuch a ſecrete and ſtraight league, as <hi>Lodouike</hi> could not ſounde in a great while after: but when hee vnderſtood it, he was greatly aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at it, and to draw the Venetians againe from the French, he practiſed a
<pb facs="tcp:18892:12"/> reconcilement betwene the <hi>Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tines</hi> &amp; them. In the end neither they nor the Pope, nor the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> nor <hi>Maximilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> (who he thought would neuer haue ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned league without comprehending him) would ſuccour him: but all fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him in the middeſt of his comming. Then hee bent himſelfe to the fortify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his owne, but putting ſuch go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours in truſt, as had more fauour then vertue (a common fault in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) he loſt one towne after another, and was driuen to forſake Millaine himſelfe, and to fortifie the caſtell: but the Towne within yeelded to the French, which newes being brought to the king at <hi>Lyons,</hi> himſelfe paſſed the mounts in perſon, and came to Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, where he compounded with al the ſtates of Italie, except <hi>Fredericke.</hi> In this meane ſpace the newe duke <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinois,</hi> who troubled <hi>Romagna,</hi> and the vicars thereof, ioyned with the French. And <hi>Baiazet Ottoman</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayled ſuch places as the Venetians held in Greece, and with ſixe hundred
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18892:12"/> horſe pilled the countrey of <hi>Friuly.</hi> And after him the duke <hi>Valentinoys</hi> tooke the Countrey, and a moſt valiant ladie of the place priſoner, and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her valew, ſent her priſoner to Rome. The French king after the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Duchie of Millaine, and that he had made truce with the king of Romanes, he returned into France, leauing ſufficient force in Italie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the cardinal of <hi>Amboyſe</hi> his lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, and <hi>Monſieur Tremouille,</hi> Captaine. <hi>Lodouike</hi> immediately recouered <hi>Como,</hi> and the <hi>Gibellins</hi> thereupon in Millaine reuolted from the French (and <hi>Trinulcio</hi> and the Frenchmen ſecretely ſtole away) hee tooke alſo <hi>Vigenene</hi> and <hi>Nouaria,</hi> but there was he betraid by the <hi>Swiſſers:</hi> &amp; yet were they contented that he and his brothers <hi>Galeas de S. Seuerin la fracaſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antonie Maria</hi> ſhould ſteale away in the habite of <hi>Swiſſers:</hi> but they were all diſcried, and hee caried away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to France, and the cardinal <hi>Aſcagnio</hi> who ſcaped, was deliuered to the
<pb facs="tcp:18892:13"/> king by the Venetians, contrarie to the olde dignitie of that ſtate. <hi>Lodouike</hi> was brought to <hi>Lyons,</hi> whom the king would not vouchſafe to fee, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his late greatneſſe and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wit: but was committed there to cloſe priſon, where after ten yeares hee miſerably ended his life. The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Aſcagnio</hi> was impriſoned in the great tower at <hi>Burdeaux,</hi> where the king himſelfe that ſent him thither, was himſelfe priſoner two yeares.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="book">
               <head>The fift Booke.</head>
               <p>THis conqueſt of Millaine by the French, made <hi>Maximilian</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke himſelfe what a ſhame it was to him to leeſe ſuch a fee of the Empire, and to ſuffer <hi>Lodouike</hi> thus to be caried away, who had put himſelfe into his protection, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hee declared himſelfe againſt the French king, and the Venetians, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading the electours and ſtates of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18892:13"/> Germanie in time to reſiſt their ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and violence.</p>
               <p>The French king proceedeth fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſuccour the Florentines againſt <hi>Piſa,</hi> taketh <hi>Bolognia</hi> into his protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and putteth garriſon into <hi>Pietre Sancte:</hi> but findeth ſuch euill ſucceſſe in his forces againſt <hi>Piſa,</hi> that he great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſtormeth at it, and offereth further power, which the Florentines in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire refuſe: finally, though he were angrie with the Pope, in that he fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him at Millaine: yet by the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the duke <hi>Valentinois, Caeſar Borgeas,</hi> he now accordeth with him.</p>
               <p>The duke in the meane time taketh <hi>Peſara</hi> and <hi>Rimini,</hi> and beſiegeth <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentia:</hi> but was ſo mightily reſiſted by the inhabitants, not inured to warre, that conſidering his forces and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent captaines, he was almoſt mad, and ſware the next ſpring, either to winne, or to die.</p>
               <p>The French king by meanes of the Archduke (for whoſe young ſonne <hi>Charles</hi> being then but three yeres old,
<pb facs="tcp:18892:14"/> he offered his daughter <hi>Claude</hi> of the ſame age) made a truce with <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> who moſt diſhonourably made no mention of the king of Naples: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that he had receiued for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand ducats, and a bond for a penſion to that end.</p>
               <p>The French king thus being ſure of the Germains, and making no doubt to obtaine the inueſtiture of Millaine, by the helpe of the Archduke, turned all his thoughtes vnto Naples, and fearing leaſt the kings of Spaine ſhould oppoſe themſelues, and that the Pope and the Venetians ſhould be iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of his greatneſſe, he now began to think it the ſureſt way to deuide it with <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of Spaine, who alſo pretended a certaine right to it: ſo that the one not to be hindered in the whole, the other to haue part of that hee had long deſired, they reſolued at one time to ſet vppon it. The French king hauing Naples, <hi>Terra de lauaro,</hi> and <hi>Abruzzo,</hi> the Spaniſh king <hi>Puglia,</hi> and <hi>Calabria,</hi> but this ſhould be kept ſecret
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18892:14"/> vntill ſuch time as the French armie were come to Rome.</p>
               <p>The duke <hi>Valentinoys</hi> beſiegeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <hi>Fauentia,</hi> &amp; ſo forceth it that they yeeld vpon condition that their young duke <hi>Aſtor,</hi> a faire prince of xviii. yeres, might inioy his libertie and reuenue: but this incarnate deuill ſent him to Rome, where after he had bene abuſed by a worſe deuill then himſelfe, in ſuch ſort as may not be expreſſed, he and a baſtard brother of his were ſecretely murthered. The duke paſſeth on and plagueth <hi>Florence,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Bolognia:</hi> but there the French king commaundeth him to ſtay, for that hee had taken the <hi>Bentiuols</hi> &amp; that ſtate into his protection. He then returneth to <hi>Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> &amp; there falleth to capitulation, after ſurpriſing certaine places of the lord of <hi>Plombin,</hi> he returneth to Rome, and ioyneth with the French king.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Frederick</hi> being thus aſſailed by theſe two mighty kings, being more inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly angrie with the king of Spaine his friend, then with the French king
<pb facs="tcp:18892:15"/> his enemie capitulated with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French, and went himſelfe into France, where he had the dukedome of <hi>Aniow,</hi> and thirtie thouſand ducats penſion. At the ſame time <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> for the Spaniſh king tooke <hi>Calabria,</hi> and <hi>Ferdinands</hi> eldeſt ſonne by compoſition: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his oath ſent him into Spain.</p>
               <p>The French king finding his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie to be enuied of the Venetians, deſired to keepe league with <hi>Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> and to warre vpon them: but the diſagreeing of the French and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh captaines in the kingdome of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, (for that the borders were not well abutted in the diuiſion) diuerted the French king to the Spaniſh wars: where finding himſelfe the ſtronger, he proteſted warre againſt <hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> if forthwith he gaue not vp his Captain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to that end ſent two thouſand Switzers, and entertained the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Salern,</hi> and <hi>Biſignan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The duke <hi>Valentinois</hi> taketh <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> and after <hi>Camerin,</hi> and repaireth to the king, who was come to <hi>Vrbin,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18892:15"/> and ſo to <hi>Aſt,</hi> where finding great grace, he put all the ſtates of Italie in great feare, inſomuch that ſecretly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe of them were driuen to confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate agaynſt him. In the which meane ſpace <hi>Gindobaldo</hi> duke of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> by a ſecrete traine of the inhabitants reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered his eſtate, and yet within a while after is driuen to flie to <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope and his ſonne plagued the familie of the <hi>Vrſins,</hi> the Pope poyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the Cardinall <hi>Vrſin,</hi> his ſon ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Paule Vrſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The French proſperity began now to decline in Naples, aſwell by their negligence and inſolencie, as by the warre: wherein <hi>Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de la Paliſſe,</hi> and diuerſe others were taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. At the length certaine bragges in words falling out on both ſides, it was agreed that there ſhould be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat of thirteene Italians againſt thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene Frenchmen, in which fight <hi>Albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> an Italian being firſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and after him <hi>Miale,</hi> with their ſwordes they killed the horſes of
<pb facs="tcp:18892:16"/> the Frenchmen, and ſo tooke them all priſoners ſauing one: who was ſlaine after he had ouerthrowne <hi>Albemount.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After this the Frenchmens hearts fayled, and peace grewe to bee trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: which not withſtanding <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> made ſtill warre, taking no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof, and tooke priſoner <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Aubigny</hi> in the ſame place, wherewith in fewe yeares before, he diſcomfited <hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> and the forces of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> being a moſt excellent captain, after that at <hi>Cirignole</hi> he gaue the French an other ouerthrow, where <hi>Monſieur de Nemours</hi> was ſlaine: fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally he paſſed through <hi>Melfe,</hi> and tooke Naples.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="book">
               <head>The ſixt Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ewis</hi> the French king hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the loſſe of Naples, of his armies and captains, when hee leaſt thought of warre: complained himſelfe highly to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18892:16"/> the Archduke, thinking that whiles he treated peace with his father in law y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king of Spaine, to be reuenged: the king &amp; Queene of Spaine on the other ſide drewe the treatiſe long, both to appoynt themſelues, and to diſappoint the French king: in the ende being ſore preſſed by the Archduke, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to quarrell with the Archduke himſelfe, ſaying that hee paſſed both his inſtructions and commiſſion, in making ſuch a diſhonourable peace as they neuer meant to make, and much leſſe to keepe: whereupon the French king prepareth to aſſaile Naples both by ſea and land. But in the meane time <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> taketh the caſtell of Naples, and beſiegeth <hi>Caiette.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Euen as fortune began to faile the Frenchmen, ſo did the Pope &amp; his ſon, gathering by his dealings with them of <hi>Bolognia</hi> &amp; <hi>Tuſcan,</hi> that there was no farther good to be done by him. And therefore being required to declare themſelues for him, they anſwered in dark ambiguities like <hi>Apollos</hi> oracles,
<pb facs="tcp:18892:17"/> for the father neuer did as he ſaid, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſonne neuer ſaid that which he did. In the end vpon much treatie, the Pope was content the French armie ſhould paſſe through the territories of the Church, and that he would not meddle with the <hi>Florentines, Sienois,</hi> nor <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lognians,</hi> during the warres, which the French king nothing beleeued, if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune frowned. But ſee the end of this Pope, as he went to ſuppe in a certaine Vineyard neare the <hi>Vatican,</hi> with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Cornetta,</hi> he was ſuddenly brought forth dead, being all blacke blowne, and hideous to looke on: his ſonne alſo was brought foorth for dead, who hauing brought two fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of impoiſoned wine, to poyſon the poore cardinal, by gods iudgement poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned his father, &amp; himſelfe, &amp; yet vſing foorthwith counterpoiſons, knowing the baite, he ſaued his life: but lay long ſicke, which quayled all his deuiſes, eſpecially in chooſing the Pope, which was <hi>Pius</hi> 3. too good a man to liue long in that place: ſo that he dying within
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18892:17"/> a few moneths, <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſeconde was choſen.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the duke <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinois</hi> is courſed by the <hi>Vrſins,</hi> dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to reconcile himſelfe to the <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nois,</hi> conſtrained to flie into the caſtle ſaint <hi>Angelo. Ceſena</hi> and other places reuolt from him to the Church againe: the Venetians are alſo in hope hereby to get <hi>Romagna,</hi> and ſoone after they take <hi>Fauentia,</hi> wherof the Pope much complaineth. And in the meane time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſteth the duke <hi>Valentinois,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoneth him in the <hi>Vatican.</hi> Thus his power that ſuddenly grewe great by crueltie, deceyt, and the Church, came as ſuddenly to nothing againe.</p>
               <p>The French king maketh warres toward Spain with ſmall profit, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon for thoſe parts a truce is taken, &amp; all the bent is to Naples. <hi>Aluiano</hi> and diuerſe <hi>Vrſins</hi> ioyne with <hi>Gonſaluo,</hi> which greatly encourageth him. The Frenchmen are repulſed at <hi>Garillani,</hi> in ſome diſorder, &amp; returne to <hi>Caiette,</hi> which after <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> taketh partly by
<pb facs="tcp:18892:18"/> force, partly by compoſition, and after is called by no other name, but the great captaine.</p>
               <p>At this time was there a peace made betweene the Venetians, and <hi>Baiazet Ottoman,</hi> who vnlike to his father, was giuen to ſtudie and learning. At this time alſo the Portingales did make their maruaylous nauigation of Eaſt <hi>Indies,</hi> paſſing the equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, leaſing the vſe of the Northwind and Loadſrone, bringing great ſpice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and other riches: but the nauigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Spaniards vnder <hi>Chriſtophoro Colombo</hi> a <hi>Geneuois,</hi> was farre more maruaylous, who ſayling thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie dayes weſtwarde, diſcouered cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Iſles neuer knowne before: and after both hee and <hi>Veſpuccius</hi> paſſing further, found firme lande, and diuerſe ciuill nations, not hauing the vſe of armes, but much golde and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The duke <hi>Valentinoys</hi> about this time eſcaped out of priſon to Naples, where <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> taketh him, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18892:18"/> him captiue into Spaine, and a truce is taken betweene the kings of Fraunce and Spaine. <hi>Fredericke</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of hope of recouering his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Naples, died, and after him Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> of Spaine: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon ſome differences were like to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe betweene the Archduke and the Spaniſh king, for the gouernement of <hi>Caſtilia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time it may not be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that Cardinall <hi>Hippolite</hi> of <hi>Eſca,</hi> being in loue with a yong damoſel his kinſwoman (who made more account of his baſtard brother) aſked her what was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe why ſhe ſo greatly loued a baſtard, and ſhe anſwered his ſweete and amiable eyes: whereupon one day as he rid on hunting, he cauſed his brother to diſmount, and commaunded his footmen in his preſence to plucke out his eyes, ſaying he liked no ſuch companions in loue.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:18892:19"/>
               <head>The ſeuenth Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Hillip</hi> the archduke began to entitle himſelfe king of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> not being content that his father in law ſhould gouerne, hauing no better intereſt then the appointment of his wife when ſhe lay in extremitie. And the king of Romanes being hartned with the greatnes of his ſonne, purpoſeth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into Italie. The French king ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them al in ielouſy (though he were verie angry with the Pope, for vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vpon the ſpiritual liuings in Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine) yet leaſt he ſhould ſtand alone, he treateth with the Pope, making quarrell to Venice, for that he knew it a thing acceptable to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip</hi> prepareth by ſea to inuade Spaine, and is by ſtorme driuen into England, where he is honorably recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth, and newly furniſhed for his voyage, vpon condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18892:19"/> that he ſhould deliuer the duke of Suffolke whom he had priſoner in the caſtell of <hi>Namures. Phillip</hi> yeeldeth, and requireth that he might not be put to death, though he pretended right to the crowne, whereunto king <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeuenth condiſcended, but <hi>Henrie</hi> the eight afterwarde ſtrake off his heade. <hi>Phillip</hi> goeth forward, and by capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion obtaineth the kingdome of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> but dieth within a while after.</p>
               <p>The French king is deſirous to bee reuenged vpon <hi>Venice:</hi> but firſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth his daughter Madame <hi>Claude</hi> vnto <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Angoleſme</hi> afterward king. The Emperour treateth with the Venetians to paſſe through their territories to be crowned at Rome. The Pope enterpriſed the recouerie of <hi>Bolognia</hi> vnder the conduct of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of <hi>Mantua,</hi> the <hi>Bolognians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ayde of the French king, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their protection: but in fine the poore <hi>Bentiuoles</hi> in ſtead of a protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had a faire ſafe conduct of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Chaumont,</hi> for which they
<pb facs="tcp:18892:20"/> payed dearly, and loſt the ſtate to the Church.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Geneuoys</hi> rebell againſt the French king, and fell alſo at ciuil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, the <hi>Gibelines</hi> fauouring the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornes,</hi> and the <hi>Guelphes</hi> the <hi>Fregoſes,</hi> euery man deſiring to bring the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment to his friendes, <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont</hi> ſetteth vpon them, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them yeeld the towne to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the king, who there entered in perſon, and pardoned all, ſauing threeſcore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and the French king, appoynted a meeting at <hi>Sauona,</hi> and there they put themſelues one in anothers power, as though there neuer had beene enmitie betweene them. Where ſupping together, none but the two kings and the Queene, the French king would needes haue <hi>Gonſaluo</hi> make the fourth, being in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of his fame, his perſon, his maieſtie in geſture and ſpeech. After this tyme this great Captaine had neuer great occaſion to exerciſe his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18892:20"/> vertue. The ende of their great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference was, that they two and the Emperour ſhoulde ioyne agaynſt the Venetians.</p>
               <p>The Emperour on the other ſide held a decree at <hi>Conſtance,</hi> for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countering of the French king in I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie, and to that end treated with the Pope, profeſſing himſelfe a protector of the Church, and an enemie of the French vſurpation in Italie, who mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (quoth he) to make the Cardinall of <hi>Amboyſe</hi> Pope, and himſelfe Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
               <p>This troubled the king, who was ſure neither of the Pope, nor of the Venetians: and the Venetians were much perplexed, whether they ſhoulde ioyne with the king, or the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: to which poyntes <hi>Foskarin</hi> and <hi>Gritti</hi> made excellent orations. In fine they anſwered the Ambaſſadour of the Emperour who demaunded paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, that if he came armed, he ſhoulde haue no paſſage: if otherwiſe they ſhoulde doe him all honour poſſible.
<pb facs="tcp:18892:21"/> He marcheth on notwithſtanding, and gaineth ſomething: but for want of good reſolution looſeth againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="book">
               <head>The eight Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow do the Emperour and the Venetians fall to trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of league, which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all Italie more afraid then euer before, which had beene al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>readie greatly tormented by the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of princes: and ſpecially by the Venetians, who made their profite of euery peace, and euery warre, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in this league with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> they demeaned themſelues ſo cunningly, that they nowe gaue cauſe both to the Emperour and the French king, to ioyne together againſt them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Pope fayled not to encourage them, inſomuch that for the Emperour Madame <hi>Marguiret</hi> his daughter, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneſſe of Flanders, for the French king, the Cardinall of <hi>Amboyſe,</hi> and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18892:21"/> for Spaine. The Ambaſſador ſware this league at <hi>Cambray.</hi> The Veneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans miſtruſting falſe meaſure, had their ambaſſadour there alſo to awaite what was done, but the Cardinall ſware ſo many othes, that the French king his maiſter woulde keepe his league with <hi>Venice,</hi> and that his mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was to make peace betweene the Archduke, and the duke of <hi>Guelders,</hi> that hee made him and the Venetians verie ſecure.</p>
               <p>This league was helde verie ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, but the Pope taking the aduaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thereof, demaunded of them <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> and <hi>Fauentia,</hi> which they had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the Church, vttering that whereas the greateſt princes in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome were ioyned agaynſt them, he would alſo ioyne, if they denied him his demaund. The Senate was deepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly amazed, and diuided in opinion tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the reſtitution, and in fine were reſolued to reſtore, had not <hi>Treuiſan,</hi> a man of high eſtate next the duke, moſt earneſtly diſſwaded them, which they
<pb facs="tcp:18892:22"/> repented: for the Pope ratified the treatiſe of <hi>Cambray,</hi> and ſo all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome in effect armed againſt them. And beſides that they had theſe euill ſignes and preſages, a ſhippe of theirs was drowned with tenne thouſande ducats. The Caſtell of <hi>Breſſe</hi> was ſtriken with thunder, their tower of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords ſuddenly fell downe, their <hi>Arſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall</hi> was burnt, twelue gallies, their ſalt peter, powder, and munition was conſumed.</p>
               <p>The French king accompanied with the duke of <hi>Loraine</hi> and nobilitie of Fraunce paſſed the Alpes, and ſent <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont</hi> afore to ſet vpon them. The Pope publiſhed a bull againſt them.</p>
               <p>The French armie ouerthroweth their battaile at <hi>Gniaradadde,</hi> taketh priſoner their chiefe Captaine <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholomeo Aluiano,</hi> who was woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the eye, as for the other Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, the Countie <hi>Petylian,</hi> he ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not, nor would aduenture all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one day, the which if hee had done,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18892:22"/> it is thought hee had ouercome: and yet his not venturing was not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked.</p>
               <p>Theſe newes aſtoniſhed almoſt vnto deſperation the Venetians: and yet that noble and graue ſtate, neyther fell to diſſention among themſelues, nor ſpake ſo much as a worde of reproch one to another, touching their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayles, that cauſed this ſucceſſe: which was ſomuch the more lamentable, for that all the Countreys ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, in this their miſerie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to ſorſake them, in ſhort, they thought it the onely way to trie by ſubmiſſion and intreatie, to diuide either the Pope or the Emperour from the French king, of whom they diſpaired. The Pope gaue ſmall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and the Emperour leſſe, without the French kings conſent.</p>
               <p>Thus the one of them gained on the one ſide, and the other on the other ſide, and the Venetians are driuen to vtter extremitie: now the ſtates of Italy, and eſpecially the Pope, ſeeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> imminent
<pb facs="tcp:18892:23"/> daungers ouer their owne heades, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan nowe to thinke what a faire threed they had ſpoonne, if the fall and ruine of <hi>Venice</hi> did bring into Italie two ſuch mightie princes on their necks: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee giueth audience to their ſixe Ambaſſadours that moſt heauily and wofully demaunded pardon: giuing the Ambaſſadours of the confederates to vnderſtand, that the Church ought not to ſhut her boſome to ſuch as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne. Now began <hi>Treuiſan</hi> to ſtand to them, and ſhortly after they recouer <hi>Padua</hi> from the Emperour, they take the Marques of <hi>Mantua</hi> priſoner.</p>
               <p>Shortly after the French king ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a league defenſiue with the Pope, returneth into Fraunce. The Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour bendeth all his forces to recouer <hi>Padua:</hi> the Venetians for the defence thereof, ſend all the yong noble and gentlemens ſonnes: with which poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie the people tooke ſuch comfort, that beyond expectation they ſo defend them ſelues, that the ſiege is rayſed, and the Emperor returneth into <hi>Allemaigne,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18892:23"/> with little profite.</p>
               <p>The Cardinall of <hi>Amboyſe</hi> hoping thereby in time to be Pope, reconcileth the Emperour and the catholike king, wherein he did his maiſter ſmall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. The Countie <hi>Petilian</hi> dieth: the Pope abſolueth the Venetians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="book">
               <head>The ninth Booke.</head>
               <p>The Pope not onely abſolueth the Venetians, but doth as it were take them into protection, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reconcile them to the Emperour, and to ſet him againſt the French king, and finally to driue the Frenchmen out of Italie: but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour woulde not heare of it without <hi>Verona</hi> were yeelded vnto him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uppon the Pope practiſeth with the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> by the meanes of the Biſhop of <hi>Sion,</hi> who now were verie proude, for that they were ſo deſired of all na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, perſwading themſelues that all the victories of king <hi>Charles</hi> and king
<pb facs="tcp:18892:24"/> 
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> came by them, and therefore pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked quarrels with the king touching their penſions. The Pope in like ſort picked quarrell to the duke of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rara</hi> for his dependancie on the French, being ſo much benefited and honoured by him. The Emperour &amp; the French king on the other ſide ſmelling his drift, to touch as well the intereſt of the one, as the other of them, knitte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againe faſt againſt <hi>Venice.</hi> And <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont</hi> for the king, and the prince of <hi>Henault</hi> for the Emperour ioyning together, draue backe the Venetian armie, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to <hi>Vincentia,</hi> the <hi>Vincentines</hi> being deſtitute of helpe, ſent an Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour to them, who made a verie pitifull oration, the which the prince of <hi>Henault</hi> anſwered with great vigor like a barbarous Dutchman. In fine they yeelded at their diſcretion, and <hi>Monſieur Chaumont</hi> treated for them, telling the prince of <hi>Henault</hi> that hee ought to haue more regard to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and glorie of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> then to the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18892:24"/> fault of the poore miſerable men, who depended on others, greater then them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
               <p>After this were taken <hi>Legnague, Montſilice</hi> and other places, &amp; <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur de Chaumont</hi> was commanded to returne to Millain, for certaine broiles there kindled cloſely by the Pope, at which time dieth the Cardinall of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyſe,</hi> which greatly hindred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> french: for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king being apter to be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then to direct, neuer had the like confidence in any man. After his death, the Pope flatly requireth the king to giue ouer his protection of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> the king anſwereth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he cannot do it with his honor, and ſo ſtomacke groweth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them. The Pope in the meane time eggeth on the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> who being angry that the king would not increaſe their penſions, were ready enough and diſcended toward Millain. The Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mean time, while <hi>Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de Chaumont</hi> was there occupied, recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red moſt part of their towns, &amp; beſieged <hi>Verona:</hi> the marques of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tua</hi> ſcaped
<pb facs="tcp:18892:25"/> out of priſon at <hi>Venice</hi> by the ſecrete meanes of <hi>Baiazet</hi> the great Turke, who had before ſhewed many friendly parts to the Marques.</p>
               <p>The Pope purpoſeth to ſet vpon <hi>Geane,</hi> and many other things that tooke no effect: the king on the other ſide, to anger him, meaneth to defende the duke of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and ſtill to continue friendſhip with the Emperour, ſo that the Pope was driuen to leaue his thoughts of getting other mens, and to thinke vpon defending his owne: for within a while after he was beſieged by <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont</hi> in <hi>Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia:</hi> but after a while he was content vpon great occaſions to leaue the ſiege, which done, the Pope complained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to all princes Chriſtian of the French king.</p>
               <p>The Pope ceaſeth not thus, but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to warres ſtill, beſiegeth <hi>Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dola,</hi> is there preſent in perſon, no leſſe buſie in bodie then in minde, riding and going to and fro like a captaine, and in the end winneth it: wherat the French
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18892:25"/> king is ſo angrie, that he ſendeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont,</hi> not onely to defend <hi>Ferrara:</hi> but alſo by all meanes to plague the territories of the Church: the Pope in the meane time is content that <hi>Modena</hi> ſhould be yeelded to the Emperiall, for feare it ſhould fal into the hands of the French. And the noble captaine <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont</hi> dieth, and <hi>Trinulce</hi> is made a Marſhall of Fraunce, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his treatiſe with the French king, is content to hearken to peace.</p>
               <p>After the death of <hi>Monſieur de Chaumont, Gaſton de Foix,</hi> a valiant yong Gentleman, and the kings ſiſters ſonne began to haue charge.</p>
               <p>The Pope partly to gaine the fauor of princes, partly to be the ſtronger in the councell that was threatned, made eight Cardinals at a clap, and among the reſt, the Archbiſhop of Yorke, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to gaine the king of England, and the Biſhop of <hi>Sion,</hi> by him to gaine the <hi>Swiſſers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now began a generall peace to be
<pb facs="tcp:18892:26"/> treated at <hi>Venice</hi> by the Biſhop of <hi>Gurce:</hi> but the Pope brake it off, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the French king commanded <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulcio</hi> to march on, who tooke <hi>Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> and after <hi>Caſtelfranco</hi> and drew to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Bolognia,</hi> they falling in great feare, the cardinall of <hi>Pauia</hi> runneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The <hi>Bentiuoles</hi> return, the popes army flieth, the Pope fretteth, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of <hi>Pauia</hi> draweth toward <hi>Rauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> to the Pope, and the duke of <hi>Vrbin</hi> hating him deadly, by the way drew his dagger, and in the middeſt of his gard ſlue him. After this the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and the French king do publiſh a councell to be holden at <hi>Piſa:</hi> the lucke whereof the Pope liked not, for that Popes had bene there depoſed at coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels holden in former times.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="book">
               <head>The tenth Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll Chriſtendome, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally al Italie ſtood at the gaze, to ſee what the French king
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18892:26"/> would do after theſe victories: for now it lay in his power (as it ſeemed) to take Rome, and all the ſtates of the Church: but he mooued either with deuotion or feare to bring all princes in his necke, commaunded <hi>Trinulcio</hi> to leaue <hi>Bolognia</hi> to the <hi>Bentiuoles,</hi> and to reſtore the reſt to the Church, and ſo to retire to Millaine.</p>
               <p>The Pope nowe to breake the necke of the <hi>Piſan</hi> Councell, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the Emperour and the French king, ſpake his Cardinals fayre, for that fiue of them had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen conſent to <hi>Piſa,</hi> and win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning backe ſome of them by fayre promiſes, publiſhed an vniuerſall Councell to bee holden at Rome, and beganne to encline to a peace with the French king: but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour dealt with the French king on the other ſide, to helpe him agaynſt the Pope, and the Venetians: but what for his pouertie and inconſtancie, the French king had no great deuotion therunto: the emperor notwithſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:18892:27"/> aduentureth, and is foyled with his French ſuccors by the Venetians: and yet after he taketh <hi>Friuly,</hi> and within ſhort ſpace looſeth it againe. The pope being newly recouered of a deadly ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beginneth to thinke againe of the chaſing the French out of Italie: the French king on the other ſide begins to be wearie of fighting agaynſt the Church: the Pope leagueth himſelfe with the Venetians, and the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique king, to deliuer Italy of ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as he pretended.</p>
               <p>The time of the Councell of <hi>Piſa</hi> drawing on, and many French Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and captaines being there, by chance there fell out ſuch a fray among the ſouldiours and ſeruants, in parting whereof, <hi>Monſieur de Chaſtillian,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de Lautrech</hi> were wounded, that the Councell was adiourned to Millaine, where they found more diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties: for all the Cleargie abſtained from diuine ſeruice, as though profane and execrable perſons, and not Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals had entred. This made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18892:27"/> king ſuſpect the Emperour, and crie out of the Catholique king, who did all contrarie to the league at <hi>Cambray:</hi> and therefore meaning to deale as falſely as the beſt, he now reſolued to ſet vpon <hi>Romagna,</hi> but in great doubt of the <hi>Swiſſers,</hi> who ſent defiance by a trumpetter vnto <hi>Gaſton de Foix</hi> his lieutenant in Millaine, the king ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth great ayde out of Fraunce, and demaundeth helpe of <hi>Florence,</hi> which is not anſwered to his expectation, by reaſon of diuerſitie of opinions. And that which was worſe, knoweth they had herein diſpleaſed the king, they ſent <hi>Guicchiardine</hi> the writer of this hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Ambaſſadour to the king of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> who ſhortly after ioyned with the Pope agaynſt <hi>Bolognia,</hi> but <hi>Monſieur de Foix</hi> came with ſuccours, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the armie to retire, and after that he wanne <hi>Breſcia</hi> from the Venetians, and ſacked it.</p>
               <p>In the midſt of this good lucke, the French king ſuddenly was appalled: for that he heard that the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
<pb facs="tcp:18892:28"/> ment to warre vpon him, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſome ſhips out of Spaine to that purpoſe. Neuertheleſſe <hi>Monſieur de Foix</hi> goeth on valiantly to <hi>Rauenna,</hi> to fight with the confederates where was fought the longeſt and nobleſt battell of all others, the Spaniards and Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians ſtriuing againſt the Frenchmen and Almaines for the glory of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And albeit in opinion the French ſeemed to haue the better: yet <hi>monſieur de Foix</hi> not abiding that the Spaniſh footmen ſhould retire in good order, ſet on them in great furie, and was ſlaine in the height of his glorie. <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Nauarre</hi> taken priſoner, <hi>Monſieur de Viuarets</hi> ſlaine before the eyes of his father, <hi>Monſieur Allegre,</hi> and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not long after the ſonne. The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie notwithſtanding entereth and ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>Rauenna:</hi> the Pope is afrayde of the newes, his Cardinals perſwade him to peace, but the king of <hi>Aragon</hi> to continue, the warres. <hi>Iulio de Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> a knight of the <hi>Rhodes,</hi> afterwarde Pope, recomforteth him alſo in ſuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18892:28"/> ſort, that he reſolueth rather to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Rome, then to make peace, and ſo much the rather, for that <hi>monſieur de la Paliſsie</hi> was departed out of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magna.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Swiſſers</hi> in the meane time paſſe the Alpes by Trent, with leaue of the Emperour towardes Millaine, and there ioyneth with the Venetian ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, <hi>Cremona</hi> yeeldeth vnto them, and <hi>Bergamo,</hi> and approching to Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, <hi>Triuulcio</hi> hauing no hope to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it for want of ſuccor, ſecretly ſtole away into <hi>Piemont. Parma, Placentia, Bolognia,</hi> and almoſt all <hi>Romagna,</hi> returne to the Pope, and <hi>Geane</hi> reuol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth from the French, making <hi>Fregoſe</hi> the Captaine of the Venetian armie their duke, which dignitie his father once had before him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="book">
               <head>The eleuenth Booke.</head>
               <p>THe duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe nowe euery way ſo weake and hard beſet (vpon aſſurance
<pb facs="tcp:18892:29"/> of ſafe conduct by the means of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and <hi>Fabricio Colonna</hi>) came to Rome, and humbled himſelfe to the Pope, as to remaine <hi>Fendatarie</hi> of the Church, the Pope would haue the dukedome it ſelfe, or nothing: the conditions being ſo hard, the duke craued pardon, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of his ſafe conduct to returne home: the Pope denied, and forged other by matters to retaine him priſoner: but the <hi>Arragon</hi> Ambaſſadour, and <hi>Fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio,</hi> for that it ſtood them vpon in honor, came ſuddenly well accompanied the next morning to the gate of <hi>Latran,</hi> and deliuered him in deſpite of the Popes garde.</p>
               <p>The French king was driuen to let the <hi>Swiſſers</hi> for a time take their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Millaine: for that he was aduertiſed that the king of Englande according to a treatiſe before holden, had ſent ſix thouſand footmen to <hi>Fown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taraby,</hi> ioyntly there to aſſayle the duchie of <hi>Gwien,</hi> and to ioyne with the Emperour, he had no hope, for that the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18892:29"/> Biſhop of <hi>Marſeilles</hi> his Ambaſſadour aſſured him it was in vaine. After this quayling of the French affaires, the Pope, the Emperour, the king of <hi>Arra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,</hi> the Venetians and Swiſſers, though they were confedered, had eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one their die vpon Millaine, but the Pope and the Swiſſers fearing the great princes, dealt earneſtly that it might be allotted to <hi>Mazimilian</hi> the yong ſonne of <hi>Lodouike Sforce</hi> to bring it from the French.</p>
               <p>The viceroy of Naples is ſent with an armie againſt <hi>Florence,</hi> the Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines receiue againe the <hi>Medici, Prato</hi> is taken by the Spaniars. The caſtell of <hi>Geane</hi> is taken by the Geneuoys, the lanterne of <hi>Geane</hi> ſtill remaineth French: <hi>Breſsia</hi> yeeldeth to the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy. <hi>Cremonia</hi> to the Venetians. The Biſhop of <hi>Gurce</hi> at Rome, treateth for a common peace.</p>
               <p>The feare of the Engliſhmen at <hi>Fowntaraby,</hi> and the negligence of the French king in not ſuccouring, cauſed the king of Nauarre, to forſake Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre
<pb facs="tcp:18892:30"/> and flie to Bearn, among the mount <hi>Pyrenes,</hi> &amp; without any charge or trauaile gat the kingdome of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre to the king of Aragon, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept certaine fortreſſes: the King of Aragon for want of title, pretending that the right thereof was giuen him by the Pope, when he curſed the French King and his adherents. But the French King endeuoureth to reconcile himſelfe both to the King of England and the Swiſſers: at the leaſt he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth to winne the Venetians from the league, and ſo with newe forces to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer Millaine. A better hope then all this was, that Pope <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond nowe died in the middeſt of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, and <hi>Iean</hi> Cardinall <hi>de Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci</hi> was choſen, named <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth: by which good accident he did the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier make peace with the Catholique King, and prepared for his purpoſe: for albeit he could not well compaſſe a peace with the King of Englande: yet for that the Engliſh were not well prouided of readie horſed, although
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:18892:30"/> their value chiefly conſiſted in foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men (yet nowe by long peace and lacke of vſe being driuen to hyre Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines) hee thought manie things might be done before that warre came forwarde: wherefore he ſent power to <hi>Triuulcio,</hi> who ioyning with <hi>Aluiano,</hi> Captaine of his newe confederates the Venetians, he ſetteth vpon the duchie of Millaine, and recouereth <hi>Geane:</hi> and after beſiegeth <hi>Nouara,</hi> where be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſiſted by the Swiſſers, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired ſeuen miles of: but the Swiſſers to the ende that no ſuccours or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might take the glorie from them, like moſt valiaunt ſouldiours hauing neither horſemen nor artillarie, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Triuulcio,</hi> and <hi>Monſieur de la Tremouille,</hi> and fought a moſt braue battaile with them, gayned their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillarie, ſlue their men with it, and put their gendarmerie to flight, who beaſtlie demeaned themſelues that day: notwithſtanding it may not bee forgotten, that <hi>Robert de la March</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his two ſonnes moſt daungerouſly
<pb facs="tcp:18892:31"/> beſet with Swiſſers, ruſhed like a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger into the midſt of them, and fought ſo terribly, that he amazed them, and deliuered his ſons. <hi>Aluiano</hi> perceiuing the diſcomfiture of the French, retired to <hi>Verona</hi> and beſieged it, but preuay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not. <hi>Padua</hi> is beſieged by the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy, and the yong duke of Millaine ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth <hi>Pontuica,</hi> by the helpe of <hi>Antonie de Leua:</hi> and the Viceroy finding that he could not take <hi>Padua,</hi> ſpoyleth the Countrey euen almoſt vnto <hi>Venice,</hi> &amp; within two miles of <hi>Vincentia,</hi> the Viceroy <hi>Proſper Celonna,</hi> &amp; the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of <hi>Peskara</hi> gaue a great ouerthrow to the Venetians, and <hi>Aluiano</hi> by the cowardiſe of their footmen of <hi>Romaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na.</hi> At the length <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians compromitted their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to the Pope: and the French king had now nothing left in Italie but the Lanterne of <hi>Geane,</hi> which alſo was battered by ſea, and defended with ſacks of wooll.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="book">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18892:31"/>
               <head>The twelfth Booke.</head>
               <p>THe king of England was nowe readie both by ſea and lande to war vpon the French king, &amp; had alſo hyred the Emperor <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> with ſixe ſcore thouſand ducats to enter al at one time into Burgundy, hoping alſo that his father in law the Catholique king woulde ioyne with him. The French king beſtirred him to reſiſt theſe great daungers, and ſome what to appall the courage of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh king, he allured into Fraunce the duke of Suffolke as a competitor of the crowne, but he being nothing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maied therewith, in deſpite ſtrake off the dukes brothers head, whom he held before in priſon by the king of <hi>Caſtiles</hi> means, as you haue heard. The French king farther to trouble him, ſet <hi>Iames</hi> King of Scots the old enemie of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land &amp; confederate of France to warre on that ſide the ſeas vppon him. The Engliſh King was long in preparing
<pb facs="tcp:18892:32"/> his ſubiects being out of vſe, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of fight being chaunged, the vſe of their bowes being almoſt gone. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe in Iuly being greatly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, his armie camped neare <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> and from thence beſieged <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win:</hi> where at the firſt they anſwered not the renowne of their hardineſſe, in that they gaue no hardie aſſault: but within a while after, they ouerthrew three hundred men of armes. The Marques of <hi>Rotelin,</hi> called duke of <hi>Longuile,</hi> Captaine <hi>Bayard,</hi> &amp; <hi>Fayette</hi> were taken priſoners, and <hi>monſieur de la Paliſſe</hi> eſcaped hardly, wherewith the French king and all France were ſo amazed, that if the Engliſh King had followed this good fortune, it is thought the gappe was nowe open to take all Fraunce. <hi>Terwin</hi> was ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the aduiſe of the Emperour, for that the Archduke <hi>Charles</hi> pretended right vnto it, and the Emperour de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the campe for that hee thought the Engliſhmen to be raſh, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſcipline. King <hi>Henrie</hi> neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18892:32"/> paſſed towards <hi>Tornay,</hi> and tooke it, whereof the French were full glad, fearing his comming farther into Fraunce with his terrible armie of foureſcore thouſand, which perhaps hee had done, if he had had experience, or had beene truly aduertiſed of the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of France: but he returned into England, aſſuring the French that he would returne the next ſommer. At this time by chaunce of fire, the richeſt part of all <hi>Venice</hi> was burnt, and the Pope endeth the differences betweene <hi>Caeſar</hi> and them.</p>
               <p>The league was renued betweene the Spaniſh king and the French king, which greatly diſpleaſed the king of England, who ſayde that this was the third time that his father in lawe had broken promiſe with him.</p>
               <p>The French king practiſed with the Pope, and the Pope with the Cardinal of Yorke to reconcile the French and Engliſh King, which tooke place, and the French king marieth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lady <hi>Mary,</hi> the king of Englands ſiſter. This was
<pb facs="tcp:18892:33"/> vnpleaſant both to the Emperour and the Spaniſh King, and not pleaſant to the Pope who was the procurer of it, who albeit he loued with ſuch cunning to gaine princes: yet he liked not that this league ſhoulde helpe the French King againe to Millaine.</p>
               <p>At this time King <hi>Emanuel</hi> of Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale preſented the Pope with two monſtrous Elephants out of <hi>India,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the xii. dieth, and <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt duke of <hi>Angoleſme</hi> ſucceedeth, taking the title of the duke of Millaine, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king peace with the King of England and the Archduke: he meaneth to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the dukedome. The Emperor, the King of <hi>Aragon,</hi> the duke of Millaine, the Swiſſers doe league againſt him: the King of England ſendeth him word to <hi>Lyons,</hi> not to paſſe into Italie to trouble Chriſtendome: the Swiſſers gard the foote &amp; ſtraights of the Alpes againſt him. But he like an induſtrious prince, by the counſaile of <hi>Triuulcio,</hi> leaueth the two ordinarie wayes of <hi>Mountſenis,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mount Genewre,</hi> and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18892:33"/> paſſeth by extreame toyle of Pioners nearer the ſea by the <hi>Cortian</hi> Alpes, by the Marquiſate of <hi>Saluzzo:</hi> and being paſſed before any man thought of him, <hi>Monſieur de la Paliſſe</hi> tooke <hi>Colonna</hi> a noble Captaine priſoner at <hi>Ville<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>france</hi> as he ſat at dinner, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſtoniſhed all Italie, inſomuch that the Pope vſed the duke of Sauoy, to excuſe him to the King forthwith.</p>
               <p>The King taketh the Countreys of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Tortona.</hi> The Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers are in diuerſitie of opinions, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they ſhall hearken to any league with the French, or farther withſtand them. At length the Biſhop of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with a very perſwaſiue oration en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged them to ioyne in one opinion agaynſt the French, and to fight with them neare vnto <hi>Marignian,</hi> where the firſt day both they and the King fought ſo long, as they could holde weapon in hand, and departed on both ſides, as it were by agreement without ſounde of trumpet.</p>
               <p>The next day they raſhly and furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb facs="tcp:18892:34"/> ſet on the French, who kept them ſelues in good order, and cauſed <hi>Aluia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> with his light horſemen to ſet on their backes, which greatly annoyed them. They fought notwithſtanding moſt valiantly: but yet diſpairing of victorie, for that the Venetian armie approched, they ſounded the retraite: and albeit the artillarie beate them on the backes, yet did they keepe their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ray towards Millaine, to the wonder of the French, and all that looked on: eſpecially the King, who often eſcaped death and daunger, and <hi>Triuulcio,</hi> who ſayde they were Giantes and not men, for that he neuer ſawe the like battell.</p>
               <p>After this victorie all the duchie of Millaine returned to the King, except the Caſtels of <hi>Cremona</hi> and Millaine, and the duke and the King fall to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and <hi>Aluiano</hi> dieth, and the Pope and the King in louing ſort talke together at <hi>Bolognia,</hi> and there renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a league with the Swiſſers, he returned into Fraunce.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18892:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> king of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and king of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> in the right of his wife, the winner of Granado, conquerour of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Nauarre, died without heire male, and the great Captaine <hi>Gonſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo</hi> died one moneth before, abſent from the Court, in diſgrace and malcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
               <p>The death of the king made the French king in hope to get Naples, thinking that the young Archduke <hi>Charles</hi> ſhoulde bee too much buſied to keepe al his eſtates, but he was diſtour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from that thought by the comming of the Emperour into Lombardie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt him and the Venetians, who ſummoned Millaine, but was faine to recule, for that by delay he loſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie.</p>
               <p>The Venetians recouer <hi>Breſcia,</hi> the Pope maketh his nephew <hi>Laurence de Medici</hi> duke of <hi>Vrbin.</hi> The King of France and Spaine make a peace at <hi>Noyan.</hi> The Venetians recouer <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rona.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:18892:35"/>
               <head>The xiii. Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eſides y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace of <hi>Noyon,</hi> the Kings of Spaine and Fraunce, and the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror treat a peace at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray,</hi> and now great quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was hoped in all Italie, ſauing that <hi>Franceſco Maria de la Rouere</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing folowed of many Spaniards, went about to recouer ſuch his ſtates as the Pope had taken from him, as <hi>Vrbin Fane,</hi> and others: driuing the Pope to complaine to the French and Spaniſh Kings, &amp; enter league with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French, for ayd agaynſt all ſubiects and fenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of the Church.</p>
               <p>The chiefe Captaines of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, that folowed <hi>Franceſco Maria,</hi> namely <hi>Maldonat,</hi> and <hi>Swares,</hi> conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after certaine victories to betray <hi>Franceſco Maria,</hi> and to deliuer him vp aliue to his enemie <hi>Laurence de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices,</hi> which treaſon <hi>Franceſco Maria</hi> diſcouering, made ſuch an excellent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18892:35"/> oration to the Spaniards, that they iudged their owne Captaines worthie to paſſe the pikes, and ſo with their owne hands ſlue them.</p>
               <p>At this time <hi>Alfonſo</hi> Cardinall of <hi>Siena,</hi> being the Popes creature, moſt vngratefully notwithſtanding conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt him: and the Cardinals of <hi>Cornette,</hi> and <hi>Volaterra,</hi> confeſſed on their knees that he had imparted it to them. <hi>Alfonſo</hi> the night following was ſecretly ſtrangled in priſon.</p>
               <p>The Pope finding himſelfe no more gracious among his colledge of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, created thirtie new Cardinals at a clappe, ſome for learning, ſome for friendſhip, and ſome for money, which nowe went low with him: and after a few conflicts with the duke of <hi>Vrbin</hi> at <hi>Ancona</hi> and <hi>Anguiare,</hi> he falleth to compoſition by meanes of <hi>Don Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues de Moncada</hi> the Viceroy, to his great charge, which the poore Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines were driuen to defray.</p>
               <p>Italy now being at quiet, the Pope began to treat with Chriſten princes
<pb facs="tcp:18892:36"/> againſt <hi>Selim</hi> the Turke: who ſeeing his father <hi>Baiazat</hi> to be olde, partly by <hi>Ianiſſaries,</hi> and partly by poyſon diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched his elder brother <hi>Achomat,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his yonger brother <hi>Corcut,</hi> and all their race, &amp; as the world ſuppoſed, had a meaning to do the like to his own ſon, the better to ſtrengthen his owne domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for his time, which by his deſperat hardnes was growne great, hauing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne the mountains <hi>Aduliens,</hi> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Sophy</hi> of Perſia, winning from him his chiefe citie <hi>Taurus:</hi> and then turned his warres vpon the Sowdan of <hi>Soria</hi> and Egypt, a moſt mightie prince of country, &amp; by reaſon of the warlike diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline of the <hi>Mamelukes,</hi> &amp; yet neuer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrown but by this <hi>Selim,</hi> who high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſdaining that his victories ſhould not be aboue <hi>Caeſar,</hi> &amp; <hi>Alexander,</hi> nowe ment to bend toward Chriſtendom, and firſt againſt <hi>Rhodes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Hungary,</hi> being verie weake, for that the king was a child, &amp; as ſome thought toward Italy, but this conſult tooke ſo ſmall effect, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if God had not ſoone after taken away
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18892:36"/> 
                  <hi>Selim,</hi> who left <hi>Soliman</hi> very yong: all chriſtendome no doubt had ſmarted for this vngodly negligence. Now was peace awhile on euery ſide, and the French &amp; the Engliſh ſo farre leagued togither, that the only daughter of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> is promiſed vpon condition to the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of France. This peace which is an enemie to great warriers, maketh <hi>Triuulcio</hi> now in his olde age to be in iealouſie with the French king for the <hi>Gwelphian</hi> faction, <hi>Monſieur de Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treck</hi> and other purſue him throughly, the king denieth him his countenance: &amp; he dieth for ſorrow in diſgrace, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as moſt great captaines do.</p>
               <p>The emperor <hi>Maximilian</hi> being now aged, treated with the electors &amp; Pope, to chooſe the king of Romans, <hi>Charles</hi> of Auſtrich, king of Spain: the French king thinking him to be too great alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, treated earneſtly to the contrarie, &amp; <hi>Maximilian</hi> dieth before any thing is done, ſo that the French and Spaniſh kings are nowe moſt earneſt compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titours and counterſutours for it.
<pb facs="tcp:18892:37"/> The French King ſpareth neither ſpeach, Ambaſſadors, perſwaſions, nor mony, and is abuſed with hope by ſome of the electours: but in fine <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Auſtrich</hi> is choſen, the which killeth the heart of the French king and his adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in Italy, and now the kingdome of Naples, the reſtitution of Nauarre vnto <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the money accorded at <hi>Nayon,</hi> begin for deſpite to come in queſtion, and into demaund.</p>
               <p>At this time the Pope abuſing all the world with his indulgences, and by the Biſhop of <hi>Arembald</hi> making a terrible exaction in diuerſe parts of Germanie, to the vſe of his ſiſter <hi>Magdalen,</hi> gaue occaſion to <hi>Martin Luther</hi> to preach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and to renue the doctrine of <hi>Iohn Hus,</hi> and <hi>Ierome</hi> of <hi>Prage.</hi> The which was verie welcom to the woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mindes of all ſuch as had felt the Popes abuſes, and ſo much the rather, as that the Pope tooke no good courſe to reſiſt it: but perſeuered ſtill in his enormities.</p>
               <p>This yeare did <hi>Charles</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18892:37"/> ariue in England, not as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Phillip</hi> did by neceſſitie, but of friendſhip, and ſo paſſed into Flanders, and to <hi>Aix,</hi> and there was crowned: in the meane time ſome broiles aroſe in Spaine, which were appeaſed by his officers.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="book">
               <head>The xiiii. Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Talie had at this time a little repoſe, but it could not long continue, by reaſon of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of theſe two great princes, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Frauncis,</hi> who could not endure the greatneſſe the one of the other, and eſpecially for that pope <hi>Leo</hi> was horne madde to want <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placentia,</hi> gotten by his predeceſſor pope <hi>Iuly,</hi> and to ſee that <hi>Ferrara</hi> ſhould ſo long holde out againſt him, maugre his head: in reſpect whereof he treated amitie with the French King, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſixe thouſand Swiſſers, and in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret they concluded to diuide the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Naples. In the meane time
<pb facs="tcp:18892:38"/> the French king taking the oportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of ſturres in Spaine, ſent <hi>Monſieur Aſperrot</hi> with a power, &amp; eaſily without reſiſtance recouered y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uarre. And the Swiſſers refuſing the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ioyned with the French.</p>
               <p>The Pope notwithſtanding his league, contracted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French king, ioineth alſo in league with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror to defend Florence &amp; the <hi>Medici,</hi> &amp; to recouer Millaine to <hi>Sforce,</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> and <hi>Placentia</hi> to the Church. At that very inſtant on S. <hi>Peters</hi> day at Millaine, there fell fire out of the ayre, which tooke certaine barrels of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which ouerthrew a fayre Marble tower, and ſo ſhooke the caſtell and city of Millaine, as a greater portent neuer chaunced vnto them.</p>
               <p>The Pope had in ſolde the Marques of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and <hi>Proſpero Colonna,</hi> and the king ſent <hi>Monſieur Lautreck</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Millaine by the helpe of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, whoſe Captaines were <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore Triuulcio,</hi> &amp; <hi>Andrew Gritti:</hi> who after they had ſkirmiſhed to and fro
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18892:38"/> with the other ſide, about the riuer of Paw: in the ende the Swiſſers hired by the Pope, ſayd that they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to defend the ſtates of the Church, for which cauſe they were purpoſely hyred: but agaynſt the French King they would not march. On the other ſide, the Swiſſers that were with the French king departed without any bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding farewell, or any worde ſpeaking. The popes army &amp; the Emperors mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth on towards Millaine: and at the firſt aſſault, the Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> Captain of the Spaniards maketh the Venetians to forſake the walles, and <hi>Triuulcio</hi> is taken and al Millaine, &amp; al <hi>Pauia</hi> and <hi>Lody,</hi> &amp; diuerſe other places yeeld, crying out vpon the French, and reioycing to become imperiall.</p>
               <p>Now died pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth (which no doubt much weakned the Emperor, for that his money beganne and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the warre) in whoſe place was choſen <hi>Adrian</hi> the ſixt a Flemming, by the fauour of <hi>Caeſar</hi> agaynſt all their minds, for that they thought a ſtranger
<pb facs="tcp:18892:39"/> of that Countrie and education, not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie fit for Italie.</p>
               <p>The duke of <hi>Vrbin</hi> recouereth his eſtate, and with the helpe of <hi>Baillous</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegeth <hi>Siena.</hi> And ten thouſand Swiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of <hi>Lucerne</hi> contrarie to the minds of <hi>Surick</hi> &amp; <hi>Suith,</hi> come ouer the mount <hi>Godard</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> into Lombardie, to helpe the French king to recouer Millaine: <hi>Proſpero Colonna</hi> is as bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie on the other ſide to defend it, and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio de Leua</hi> to defend <hi>Pauia. Mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſieur de Lautreck</hi> beſiegeth it, which he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth in time to get by famine: but their induſtrie within deceyueth his hope. Wherupon <hi>Lautreck</hi> retireth towards Fraunce, and three thouſand of his Swiſſers were ſlain at <hi>Bicoque</hi> by the emperiall armie. <hi>Lody</hi> alſo and <hi>Gene</hi> were taken by them.</p>
               <p>At <hi>Lucques</hi> at this time <hi>Poggio,</hi> and <hi>Totty,</hi> two men of noble familie, vnder colour of priuate enmitie, in the open palace ſlue the <hi>Gonfalonier</hi> of that ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: but afterward were chaſed by the citizens. <hi>Saguſanac Malateſte</hi> vſurpeth vpon <hi>Rimini.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="book">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18892:39"/>
               <head>The xv. Booke.</head>
               <p>THe French King being euerie where at peace, his returne into Italy is ſuſpected, and therfore <hi>Florence, Geane, Siena,</hi> and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> are taxed with great ſummes for the maintenance of a continuall armie to defend Naples and Millaine, and <hi>Don Charles de Lanoy</hi> is made Viceroy of Naples. The Pope taketh his iourney towards Rome, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour into Spaine, and talketh with king <hi>Henrie</hi> of England by the way, &amp; they two ioyntly ſent Ambaſſadours to Venice, to perſwade them to leaue the amitie of the French king, and to ioine with the Emperour. The king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land moreouer ſent an Herault to the French king, to proteſt warre againſt him, in caſe he would not make truce with the Emperour for three yeares, the which woulde not be granted: but the league betweene the Emperour and the Venetians ſucceded, and touching
<pb facs="tcp:18892:40"/> the ſame, two excellent orations were made by <hi>Andrew Gritti,</hi> and <hi>George Cornare.</hi> While chriſtian princes were thus vndermining and vexing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Soliman Ottoman</hi> the Turke in perſon with infinite power beſieged the <hi>Rhodes:</hi> the which though it were to the vttermoſt defended by the grand maiſter and the knights thereof, yet by the negligence of the pope &amp; chriſtian princes, they were faine to yeeld, and on Chriſtmaſſe day the Turke in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph entered, and dedicated all the Churches to <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The French kings armie being now paſſing the Alpes, and himſelfe readie in perſon to follow, he diſcouered that the diſcontented duke of Burbon, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of Fraunce, was conſpired with the Emperor &amp; the King of England, and ſhould marrie with <hi>Elenor</hi> the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſiſter, widow of <hi>Emanuel</hi> late king of <hi>Portingale,</hi> and that aſſoone as he was ouer the Alpes, the duke of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, and the King of England ſhould ſet vpon Fraunce, and the duke ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18892:40"/> be King of Prouence, and the King of England ſhould haue the reſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe newes, though they appalled and ſtayed the Kings perſon, yet did it breake the attempt, and cauſed the duke to flie in a ſtraunge weede, firſt into <hi>la Franche Conte,</hi> and after to Millaine. In the meane time, Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> dieth, and the Cardinal <hi>de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices</hi> is choſen, calling himſelfe <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the ſeuenth.</p>
               <p>The French armie being now paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Alpes, <hi>Monſieur de Boniuet</hi> a French Captain taketh <hi>Loda,</hi> the reſt of the French power being vnder the conduct of the Admirall before Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine, were not in great hope to take it, but making diuerſe ſkirmiſhes, ſtill came by the worſt. And ſhortly after retyred from thence, in which meane ſpace the noble Captain <hi>Proſpero Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonna</hi> died.</p>
               <p>The Pope refuſed to be of either ſide, whereof the French King is glad, &amp; the Emperour verie angrie: for that he hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him to that dignitie. The Emperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als
<pb facs="tcp:18892:41"/> paſſe the riuer of <hi>Theſin,</hi> and foyle the French in diuers places, inſomuch that they begin to abandon the duchie of Millaine, but in warlike aray. The Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> followeth with light horſes, and <hi>Chabanes</hi> is ſlain, and captaine <hi>Bayard</hi> is taken priſoner, who died of his wounds: and the Admirall returneth into Fraunce. After which time the duke of Burbon counſailed the Emperour to turne the warres in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Fraunce, alledging that the deſire the Engliſh king had to conquer that realme, would much helpe him. The King of England alſo much encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the Emperour thereunto: but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the difficulties and charge for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and being diſſwaded by the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious cardinall of Yorke (who was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly French) he moued little.</p>
               <p>The Emperor vpon this confidence maketh warre in <hi>Prouance:</hi> the duke of Burbon and Marques <hi>Peſcara</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Captaines. The duke would haue paſſed on into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bowels of France: but the Marques &amp; other captaines would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18892:41"/> by no meanes from the ſeas, but lay in ſiege before <hi>Marſiles</hi> fortie daies with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out profite. And for that before their comming they hoped that the king of England would ſo haue fired y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French king on his ſide, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his forces ſhould haue bent that way, &amp; that they ſhould haue receiued money out of Englande, (which both they failed of) they thought it folly to go any farther, or to abide til the king with his whole power, and ſix thouſand Swiſſers ſhould come vpon them, and therefore with ſpeede retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into Italy: wherewith the king be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in heart, followed as faſt, &amp; al in one day the king came to <hi>Verceil,</hi> and the Marques of <hi>Peſcara:</hi> albeit forthwith it was agreed by the Viceroy, and the reſt, that <hi>Antonio de Leua,</hi> ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend <hi>Pauia,</hi> and the other Millaine, which was ſore infected with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plague, that they durſt ſcarcely furniſh it, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that the maine armie of Fraunce being at hand, ere they could well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide, the captaine <hi>Alarcon</hi> was faine to leaue it: and the King tooke it, vſing al
<pb facs="tcp:18892:42"/> clemencie, notwithſtanding he knewe the French to be there hated. From thence he beſiegeth <hi>Pauia,</hi> but could not take it: and ſendeth <hi>Stuart</hi> duke of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bany</hi> in Scotlant with a power to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. The pope perſwadeth them to peace.</p>
               <p>The duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> being come into the French kings protection, helpeth him againſt <hi>Pauia,</hi> but it is ſuccored by the Emperials. The pope &amp; the French captaines perſwade the king to deſiſt, but he ſayth he will either win or die. At the length on S. <hi>Mathias</hi> day, on which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperor was borne, the Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy and the Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> in well ordered battell ioyned with the King, who fought nobly, being hurt in the face, and in the hand, vntill his horſe was ſlain vnder him, and after was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by fiue common ſouldiours, that knew him not, but in the end he diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red himſelfe to the Viceroy, who recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued him as priſoner to the Emperour. <hi>Antonie de Leua</hi> in the meane time throwing downe ſo much of the wall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18892:42"/> of <hi>Pauia,</hi> as an hundreth horſes abreſt might come through, iſſued out, and ſet on their backe, ſpoiling and putting to flight all, ſauing the rereward of the duke of <hi>Alanſon,</hi> taking priſoner the king of Nauarre, the baſtard of <hi>Sauoy, Montmorancie,</hi> and others, and manie of the Nobles and beſt captaines were there ſlaine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="book">
               <head>The xvi. Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll the Potentates of Italie were nowe greatly diſmaied with this taking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, fearing the greatnes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, ſepecially the Pope: and next him the Venetians, who treated a league with the Pope, offering to ioyne in theſe common dangers, &amp; to leuy ten thouſand Swiſſers, and a ſufficient band of Italians, not doubting the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe of my Ladie Regent of France, to ſend y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke of Albany with ſufficient ſuccors, and making ſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> duke of <hi>Ferrara.</hi> The viceroy
<pb facs="tcp:18892:43"/> on the other ſide was carefull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey the kings perſon into ſome place of ſuretie, &amp; to make all ſure, to ioyne in amitie with the pope. The Pope bit at the baite immediatly &amp; was full glad, and treated to bring in the Venetians alſo, but that would hardly be: for that they would not drop ſo much money as the Viceroy demaunded.</p>
               <p>The Pope ſendeth the Biſhop of <hi>Piſtoia</hi> to viſite &amp; comfort the French king. The Emperour being in Spaine receyueth the newes of this victorie, &amp; his confeſſour the Biſhop of <hi>Oiſme</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth an eloquent oration, perſwading him franckly and freely to deliuer the French king, and that to be the moſt profitable, honourable, and ſure way: <hi>Fredericke</hi> duke of <hi>Alba</hi> ſpake to the contrarie with great vehemencie, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that to let him go were dangerous, and to let him go moſt honorably, were nothing to the Frenchmen, who were inſolent and light, and made no regard of honour: and therefore to make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of him were the beſt way. In fine,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18892:43"/> the Emperour ſent vnto him his great chamberlaine <hi>Monſieur de Beaucain</hi> to <hi>Piſqueton</hi> to comfort him, &amp; to tell him that theſe were his conditions: hee ſhould depart with the ſoueraigntie of the dukedome of Burgundie to him: he ſhould depart with Prouance to the duke of Burbon, with many other great things, both for him, and for the king of England. The French king anſwered conſtantly, that he would die in priſon before he would diminiſh the crowne of Fraunce, for all other things, he would ſatiſfie the Emperour with reaſon.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the Ladie Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent of Fraunce employed all meanes poſſible, and eſpecially the Cardinall of Yorke, to winne the king of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, where all the feare was.</p>
               <p>The Emperour on the other ſide ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited the King of Englande to ioyne with him to conquer Fraunce: but the King demaunded the whole kingdome in effect, if it were conquered, &amp; ſome other ſuch conditions, as gaue them
<pb facs="tcp:18892:44"/> cauſe to breake off.</p>
               <p>The Imperials become inſolent in Italie, the French king is conueyed into Spaine, &amp; impriſoned at <hi>Madril,</hi> &amp; the duke of Burbon is ſent for (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom the Emperor will make no agreement) and being placed in the houſe of a great barron at the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors requeſt, he anſwered that he would obey, for that he and all was at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. But ſo ſoone as the duke were gone, he would ſet it on fire with his owne hands, leaſt it ſhould ſmell of the infection of a traitor.</p>
               <p>There is now a conſpiracie againſt the Emperour in Italy, wherein the Marques of <hi>Peſcara</hi> plaid a part at the firſt, and after accuſed the reſt diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, and ſhortly after died. In the meane time the French king falleth extreamly ſicke at <hi>Madril,</hi> inſomuch that the Emperor in perſon would haue viſited him, but his Chauncelor would not ſuffer him. Within a while after the Emperour eſpouſeth the infant of <hi>Portingale:</hi> the French king recouereth
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18892:44"/> health, the Pope treateth for his deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, touching the which the great Chancellor and the Viceroy make two excellent orations.</p>
               <p>After this ſhortly enſueth the treatiſe of <hi>Madril</hi> for the kings deliueraunce, wherin was yeelded <hi>Burgu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>die, Chare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lois,</hi> and ſo many other Countreys, as they that heard it, did thinke it would neuer be kept: for aſſurance hereof the king was affianced to the Emperours ſiſter <hi>Elconor:</hi> and the <hi>Dolphin</hi> of Fraunce and the duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> were brought in a boat to the midſt of the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that deuideth Spaine &amp; Fraunce, and the king in another boate, and at one inſtant they chaunged boates, and the king haſted to land, and had a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh horſe readie, with whom he rid in poſt to Bayon, and there met with a meſſenger from the king of England, which greatly comforted him, vnto whom he confeſſed, that he acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the greateſt cauſe of his deliuery to proceed from him, and therfore he was for euer the Engliſh kings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="book">
               <pb facs="tcp:18892:45"/>
               <head>The xvii. Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough both the Emperour and the King, had ſworne to the conditions ſet downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them for his deliuerie, and that the king farther ſware to ratifie them, ſo ſoone as he came into a place of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, Neuertheleſſe as ſoone as hee came to <hi>Bayon,</hi> he anſwered the meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger that attended the ratification, that he durſt not performe ſuch things as were preiudiciall to the crowne of France, vntill he had wonne the minds of his ſubiects vnto it. After that hee highly complained himſelfe to all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and eſtates of the Emperours ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritie, as well touching the hard con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, as that hee would not once vouchſafe to ſee him during his impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment: that his ambition grewe ſo great, that he now meant to ruine the Pope, the Church, all Italy, and to bring all Chriſtian princes into ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection. With theſe perſwaſions he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18892:45"/> to bring al Italy and other princes to ioyne with him, and conſequently to bring the Emperour to ſuch daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous warre, as he ſhould of neceſſitie be driuen to releaſe Burgundie, and other hard conditions for money.</p>
               <p>The Emperiall armie on the other ſide waxing euery day in Italy more and more inſolent, &amp; being extreamely chargeable to the <hi>Millanois,</hi> and <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio de Leua</hi> himſelfe, hauing euerie day thirtie ducats, the people in tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſort tooke weapon in hand, and had driuen away both captaines and ſouldiours, had not the cunning of the captaine, and their owne diſorder com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the matter.</p>
               <p>The Emperour ſent the Viceroy of Naples into Fraunce, to accept the perfourmance of the conditions: where he was greatly welcomed, but nothing was performed. The Emperour was neare madde for anger, and ſo much the more, as that almoſt againſt all mens opinion, and contrarie to the intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ladie <hi>Margueret</hi> Regent of
<pb facs="tcp:18892:46"/> Flaunders, he would needs inſert the article of Burgundie, which they aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him would neuer be performed: but happily breed further broyle.</p>
               <p>In the meane time at <hi>Coignac</hi> there is treated a league betweene the pope, the French King, the Venetians, and the duke of Millaine, to be forthwith intimated to the Emperor, who had li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to enter into it within three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths: ſo that he deliuered the French kings children at a reaſonable ranſome to be rated by the King of Englande. After this treatie the Pope ſurpriſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> letters of <hi>Antonio de Leua,</hi> touching the hard eſtate of the duke of Millaine, and the duke of <hi>Vrbin,</hi> generall of the Venetians armie, taketh <hi>Loda,</hi> and ſo paſſeth to Millaine: where after long batterie, they were faine to retire with ſome altercation betwene the duke and the lieutenant.</p>
               <p>The Spaniards in the meane time ſo plagued the <hi>Millanois,</hi> that one of them made a very lamentable oration to the duke of <hi>Burbon</hi> (who was there ariued)
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18892:46"/> and yet finding no remedie, but a cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous anſwere: ſome hanged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſome threw themſelues out at their windowes, and ended their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with other deaths. The armie of the confederates once againe appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth towards Millaine, but not onely doth any good, but alſo the Caſtell it ſelfe by the duke is vpon conference with the duke of Burbon, yeelded to the Imperials.</p>
               <p>While chriſten princes were thus tearing out the bowels one of another, <hi>Soliman Ottoman</hi> Turke, entreth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hungarie, and putteth the whole Countrey, and conſequently all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome in daunger, ouerthrowing <hi>Lewis</hi> the young King, and getteth a great part of that buckler of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>The Pope, notwithſtanding encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth his confederates to ſet vppon Naples, and <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Nauarre</hi> is made generall: and all the confederates offer the Emperour to enter into the league, perfourming the conditions:
<pb facs="tcp:18892:47"/> he anſwered, he could not with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, being a league made againſt him eſpecially, and yet for a common quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he would do it preſently, if the meſſengers had ſufficient commiſſion: meaning in deed nothing leſſe, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to keepe the king of England from entering into it.</p>
               <p>Rome is ſurpriſed by the <hi>Colonois,</hi> and the Pope driuen to leaue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and to deale with them: and the confederates by ſea fight with the Emperials.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="book">
               <head>The xviii. Booke.</head>
               <p>THe French King and the Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians had the Pope in great iea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie, that hee woulde forſake their league, in that he made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie treatiſes with the Viceroy: and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer cried out of the charges of the warre, and yet would not make money by creating of Cardinals, nor other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, as other Popes did: but to break y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> treatiſe (if there were any ſuch)
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18892:47"/> they vrged him, and bent themſelues with him by ſea againſt Naples. The popes Lieutenant was <hi>Monſieur Vau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demont,</hi> who pretended right thereto by ancient title of king <hi>Rene:</hi> where after certaine exploites of no great waight, the Pope ſeeing no greater ſucceſſe, and that the duke of Burbon by the perſwaſion of the duke of <hi>Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> drew towards Rome, and that the French promiſes were but winde, he fell to agree a truce for eight moneths with the Viceroy. The duke of Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon neuertheleſſe would not accept of it, but marched on. The Viceroy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in perſon went from Rome, to make him ſurceaſe, but all in vaine: for the dukes caſe being now ſomewhat deſperate, he draweth to Rome, and either meaneth to get that noble bootie or to die: and therefore moſt valiantly giueth the aſſault himſelfe before all men, and was ſlaine with a harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buze. His death enflameth the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and eſpecially the Lanceknights, who before were verie cold: inſomuch
<pb facs="tcp:18892:48"/> that within fewe houres they take the towne and ſacke it, where they had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite treaſure.</p>
               <p>The palaces of the Cardinals were rifled, and the Cardinal of <hi>Siena,</hi> who himſelfe &amp; all his anceſtors were Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall, was yet driuen to compound with the Spaniards: &amp; yet after (as in all ſuch broyles no man is ſure) he was taken priſoner by the Launceknights, and caried bareheaded with many buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fets to <hi>Borgo,</hi> where he paied a newe raunſome of fiue thouſand ducats. In like maner were vſed all the Spaniſh and Dutch prelats: notwithſtanding the hope of their Countrey-mens fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour.</p>
               <p>The Pope driuen to keepe himſelfe in the caſtell, vntill the plague wearied his enemies, and compoſition made with the Imperials. The Emperour being certified of the Popes diſtreſſe, and that the plague was entred into his caſtell of S. <hi>Angelo,</hi> made outward ſhew of diſlike, but inwardly was very glad, and indeed he had cauſed him to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:18892:48"/> be caried into Spain, had it not beene for feare of the king of England: as for the French king, he cared not if the Pope had bene hanged, and all Italie fiered, ſo that he had againe his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal of Yorke is now ſent into France, to make a league with the French king more ſure, and to offer the mariage of the Lady <hi>Marie</hi> either to the king, if he went not on with the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours ſiſter, or otherwiſe to the duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi> And for that the Cardinal was honourably accompanied with xii. hundred horſes, &amp; had three C. thouſand crownes to lend the king towards his warres with the Emperour. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of Loraine was firſt ſent to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him, and after the king himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him at <hi>Amiens.</hi> In fine, the king and he ſent <hi>Gambare</hi> to the Pope, to make the Cardinall of Yorke his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car generall in Fraunce, England and Germanie, during his impriſonment: but ſecretly the French king withſtood it by all meanes poſſible.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:18892:49"/>
               <p>In this meane ſpace, the French armie vnder the conduct of <hi>Monſieur de Lautreck</hi> take <hi>Boſco,</hi> and <hi>Genes</hi> by compoſition, after the Countrey of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> and then <hi>Pauia,</hi> where the ſouldiours ſacked and pilled, and vſed crueltie eight dayes in memorie of the battell of <hi>Pauia,</hi> where the king was taken. The duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> entereth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the league with him, in reſpect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Madame <hi>Rence,</hi> daughter of king <hi>Lewis</hi> the xii. is promiſed to his ſonne <hi>Hercules,</hi> and after the Marques of <hi>Mantua</hi> entred into the ſame league.</p>
               <p>The treatiſe of peace ſeemed vaine betweene the Emperour and the king: for the Emperor ſayd he could not truſt the king that had once deceiued him. The Kings ambaſſadors replied, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for aſmuch as he tooke himſelfe to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, the King might the leſſe truſt him. In the ende the ambaſſadours of Fraunce and England denounced war agaynſt him: and many hot ſpeeches breeding hot choler, the Emperor cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenging the combat of the French king
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18892:49"/> ſaid, he was a falſe forſworn king. The French king on the other ſide gaue him the lie.</p>
               <p>The king of England embraceth the religion of <hi>Luther,</hi> and by the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the Cardinall of Yorke, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorceth his wife <hi>Katherin</hi> of <hi>Arragon. Monſieur de Lautrech</hi> entreth the kingdome of Naples, and <hi>Andro Dore</hi> being at the ſould of the king with his gallies, returneth to <hi>Geane,</hi> diuerſe places yeeld vnto <hi>Lautreck,</hi> and by him Naples it ſelfe is beſieged.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="book">
               <head>The xix. Booke.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Onſieur de Lautreck</hi> finding the value of the defendants of Naples, to be great, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to continue the ſiege, hoping that though vertue fayled not, yet want of money and victuall would make vertue yeeld to neceſſitie. In the meane time <hi>Phillippin Dore</hi> with his gallies and <hi>Geneuois,</hi> who were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſea-men, did ſinke diuerſe ſhippes
<pb facs="tcp:18892:50"/> Imperiall vpon the ſea, ſleaing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy <hi>Don Hugues di Moncada,</hi> &amp; <hi>Fiera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſque,</hi> with diuers other, to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a thouſand, &amp; taking priſoners y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Marques of <hi>Guaſt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Aſcagnio Colo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na,</hi> the prince of <hi>Salerne,</hi> and diues others.</p>
               <p>This conqueſt of the ſea would not make Naples yeeld, for <hi>Phillippin Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> tooke ſuch direction of <hi>Andro Dore</hi> to retire to <hi>Pozzouolo,</hi> that Naples was oft vittailed, &amp; the Venetian fleet, after they had gotten <hi>Ottranto</hi> ſtaied in hope to win the caſtell of <hi>Brunduſium,</hi> ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defendants were encouraged, and the aſſailants for lacke of water and other neceſſaries fainted, and in the meane time <hi>Antonio de Leua</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuing that <hi>Pauia</hi> was negligentlie kept, aſſaulted it by night, and tooke it, and had the Captains priſoners before the ſouldiers were awares.</p>
               <p>The Pope continued his newtrality betweene the two princes, and ſo was neither truſted of the French king, nor of the Emperour, who the more ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, for that he had ſent Cardinall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18892:50"/> 
                  <hi>Campeius</hi> into England to diuorce his kinſwoman Queene <hi>Katherin,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Aragon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now doth <hi>Andro Dore</hi> leaue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſould of the king, and entreth ſould with the emperor, vpon conditions: &amp; the french army before Naples is full of diſeaſes, <hi>Monſieur de Vaudemont</hi> almoſt dead, <hi>Monſieur de Lautreck</hi> very ſicke, and ſhortly after dieth: ſo that the Marques of <hi>Saluzzo</hi> is driuen to capitulate with the prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who is now vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy. <hi>Monſieur de S. Poll</hi> gained cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine townes in Lombardy for the French, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meane time <hi>Andro Dore</hi> taketh <hi>Geane</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperials, through the groſſe negligence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French king.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Monſieur de S. Poll</hi> marcheth on ſtil through Lombardy, &amp; comming within xii. miles of <hi>Pauia: Antonio de Leua,</hi> who had beene long ſicke, cauſeth himſelfe to be caryed in a chayre, and all his men to put on white ſhirtes, and ſtealeth without noyſe one night to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the French, within two miles of <hi>Ladriane,</hi> &amp; vnawares ſetteth
<pb facs="tcp:18892:51"/> on <hi>Monſieur de S. Poll,</hi> who albeit he fought valiantly, truſting to his Lance-knights, yet they ranne away, and he remained priſoner with <hi>Caſtillon, Claude Rangin,</hi> and diuerſe others, to <hi>Antonio de Leua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now beginneth the Pope to treate a peace at <hi>Barcelone</hi> with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, greatly to the Popes aduauntage, both for that he ſhould forget iniuries paſt, &amp; be no hinderance to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, who ment perſonally to make a voyage into Italy. The like was trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted betweene the French King and the Emperour at <hi>Cambray,</hi> a place deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied to ſuch great treatiſes, being there preſent the two ladie Regents, for the two princes, the Ambaſſadours of the confederates, and the duke of Suffolke, and the Biſhop of London for the King of England. The French King being ſomewhat aſhamed of this act, for certaine dayes kept himſelfe cloſe, and would not be ſeene of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of his confederates: in the ende he gaue them ſweet wordes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:18892:51"/> and promiſes, excuſing himſelfe, that otherwiſe hee could not haue his children.</p>
               <p>The Emperour after this, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to aſſaile the Florentines, and himſelfe in royal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon commeth to <hi>Geane,</hi> where the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Italy do ſalute him by their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours.</p>
               <p>The King and the Pope talked togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at <hi>Bolognia,</hi> the pope entring firſt, as the greater princes vſe. The Turke left off beſieging Vienna: the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour is inclined to capitulate with the Venetians, and <hi>Francis Sforce,</hi> to whom he reſtored the dukedome of Millaine, and the Venetians to the Church that they held in <hi>Romagnia,</hi> and to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror that which they held in <hi>Puglia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="book">
               <head>The xx. Booke.</head>
               <p>THeſe late leagues ſeemed nowe to eſtabliſh peace each where, ſauing only to the poore Floren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, who often had helped o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb facs="tcp:18892:52"/> to make their peace, and now the peace of others drew them to a daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous warre with the Emperour, who now ſent againſt them foure thouſand Lanceknights, and three thouſande Spaniards and Italians vnder the prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> which maketh <hi>Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cara</hi> and <hi>Prato</hi> yeeld of themſelues to the Pope, and the ſouldiours of France being well payd, defended themſelues valiantly.</p>
               <p>In the meane time the Pope cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the French king to ſend <hi>Monſieur de Cleremont</hi> to Florence, to excuſe himſelfe, for not comprehending them in the league vpon neceſſitie of recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his children, wiſhing them to take ſuch conditions as they could get in ſo hard a caſe, wherein himſelfe would be a dealer for them.</p>
               <p>The Emperour meaning to go to Rome to be crowned, being letted with certaine importunate affaires of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie, and chiefly to elect his brother <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> king of Romanes, was faine to be crowned at <hi>Bolognia, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18892:52"/> 1530, on his birth day of S. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias,</hi> which was his fortunate day, and there the Pope and the duke of <hi>Ferrara</hi> compromitted all their differences vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
               <p>The Florentines being often ſkir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed withall, and often battered, though they valiantly defended (after the death of the prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and departure af the Marques of <hi>Guaſt</hi>) were yet for verie hunger and diuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of opinions, driuen to offer to <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſague</hi> the Captaine of the Imperials, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe and the Pope ſhoulde determine their conditions and gouernment, their life and libertie ſaued.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> is now choſen King of Romanes at a decree in Auſbourge, and there is treatiſe agaynſt the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therians,</hi> of whom the great princes beganne to be afrayde: and at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant requeſt of the Germaines, the Emperour ſummoned the Pope to call a Councell: the Pope vtterly miſliked it, as preiudiciall to his Court, and
<pb facs="tcp:18892:53"/> abuſes, and yet diſſembled it cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly.</p>
               <p>The French would neuer bee long quiet, but the King turneth to his olde emulation of the greatneſſe of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and perſwadeth with the Pope and ſtates of Italie to take heed of it. To the ſtates of Germanie, he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that the Emperour ment to make it a Monarchie. The King of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land he pricketh forwarde, in recoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto him how angrie the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour was for the diuorce of his mothers ſiſter: and laſt of all, that which euill beſeemed the moſt Chriſtian King, he ſtirreth vp the Turke, who indeede was alreadie iealous of his greatneſſe, and hated him alſo in reſpect of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with whom he was at oddes for Hungarie.</p>
               <p>The Emperour ſtill calleth vpon the Councell, he deſireth now to renue the league of <hi>Bolognia,</hi> and to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende in it all Italie, making contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for their common defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the French. The Pope lyked
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18892:53"/> not to be of any ſide, remembring the daungers paſt ſo often as the ſides were ouerthrowne, but being of that calling, he liked neutralitie better, as the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt way.</p>
               <p>The Emperour returneth into Spaine, and the Pope and the French king talke at <hi>Marſeilles</hi> of great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, vnder pretence of dealing againſt the Turke, and the King of Englands diuorce. To ratifie their matters, <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin</hi> of <hi>Medices</hi> the Popes neece, was married to <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond ſonne of Fraunce, whome nowe the Pope woulde faine make duke of Millaine forthwith: for he foreknewe (as it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) that he ſhould ſhortly die, in that he made his Ring, and all other habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, and indeed died, in whoſe place was choſen <hi>Alexander Farneſe,</hi> called <hi>Paule</hi> the third.</p>
               <p>The duke of <hi>Wittemberg,</hi> by ayde of the Lantgraue of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> and the French Kings money, recouered the dukedome from <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and great troubles were toward: but the matter
<pb facs="tcp:18892:54"/> was compounded without the French kings conſent, who in the meane time hoped to get Millaine.</p>
               <p>At this time alſo <hi>Barbaroſſa Baſcha</hi> generall by ſea to <hi>Soliman,</hi> paſſing to the conqueſt of <hi>Thunis,</hi> ſcoured the riuers of <hi>Calabria,</hi> and paſſed <hi>Caiette,</hi> and put all Italie in ſuch a feare, as he might eaſily haue taken Rome, if he had come forward.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18892:54"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
